Finding aid to Smith College Relief Unit records CA.MS.00095
Smith College Archives
Smith College Relief Unit records
1904-1997
Smith College Archives
Smith College Relief Unit.
CA.MS.00095
9.125 linear feet (25 containers)
The Smith College Relief Unit was founded in 1917 to bring relief to those areas of France that were most devastated during the first World War. The records include letters, journals, photographs and albums, correspondence with the War Service Board and information about the reconstruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Smith College Relief Unit was founded in 1917 by Harriet Boyd Hawes (1892) to bring relief to those areas of France that were most devastated during the first World War. Hawes already had significant experience of relief work when she proposed, at a Boston Smith Club meeting in 1917, to form the unit. She had served as a relief nurse in both the Greco-Turkish war of 1897 and the Spanish American war, and then later in France, when WWI began. Having seen first-hand the effects of the war in Europe, Hawes was dismayed at the apathy expressed towards it by Americans when she returned to the States. When the US finally did join the war, Hawes quickly announced her intentions of starting a relief unit, which she hoped to staff with other Smith graduates. Smith alumnae were eager to lend their services; a Committee of Five was established to manage business in the US, and the necessary money was soon raised. The group attained the recognition of the State Department early on, and an affiliation was established with the American Fund for French Wounded through Harriet's previous connections in France. By 1918 the Red Cross accepted the unit as an affiliate.
That summer, with a pledge of $30,000 from alumnae, Hawes set off with seventeen other Smith graduates for France. Their base was to be in the village of Grecourt in the devastated Somme Valley, chosen by the French government as the area of greatest need. When they arrived in Grecourt, the women of the Unit found that not a single building had been left intact; the Germans bombed everything before they left and deported all the able-bodied youth, leaving only the old and the sick and those children who were too young to work. Any machinery that might have been a help to the villagers had been broken, and once-fertile fields were unrecognizable. The primary interest of the Unit was in helping the villagers to regain self-sufficiency. As much as was possible the Unit bought from the villagers food for themselves and fodder for their livestock, much of which was sold back to the villagers at well below original cost. A store was established from which basic staples and supplies were sold. The Unit also kept a truck which they used as a "traveling store." The SCRU rebuilt St. Matthew's Church and revived services by bringing a minister to the town. They built a school, a library and hospital, planted fruit trees, wheat and vegetables and provided medical services. Sewing was given out to the local women, for which the women were paid according to scales established by the French government. The SCRU taught classes to children, including carpentry, sewing, cooking, music, games and physical education, along with a curriculum of reading and arithmetic.
In March of 1918 a new German offensive forced the evacuation of Grecourt and the surrounding villages. The Unit relocated for a time in Beauvais, where the members worked with the Red Cross to treat the American wounded. Many of the volunteers, having finished their required terms, and having seen more of battle than they bargained for, returned to the States. Among these was Hannah Dunlop Andrews, the director of the Unit, who felt she must give up her position in order to return home with her husband, a Major in the American Army. When the war ended, a new director, Marie Wolfs, was appointed and the Unit returned to Grecourt. The village was even more devastated than at the time of their first arrival, and much of their work had been lost.
The Red Cross began to disband their relief services that November, and the SCRU was an independent organization again. Those who stayed on at Grecourt did so at the request of the French government and out of a sense of commitment to and investment in the project. The last of the Unit's members did not leave France until 1929, by which time they had rebuilt and improved upon all that was lost in the German strike of 1918. The Smith College Relief Unit was the first college women's unit in France and the first to be acknowledged by the Red Cross. Inspired by the Smith Unit, several other colleges followed, including Wellesley and Bryn Mawr.
In 1919 the Union des Femmes de France (a French branch of the Red Cross) awarded the women the Medaille de Guerre in recognition of their work in the evacuation of March 1918, and in 1920 the French government awarded the Unit the silver medal of Reconnaissance. The Croix de Guerre was awarded to those villages that the Unit served, for bravery under German occupation, and at Smith, the Grecourt Gates, a replica of those that stood in front of the Chateau de Robecourt, were erected by the Trustees of the College in front of College Hall.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Smith College Relief Unit include directors' reports, financial information, letters, journals, photographs and albums, news clippings, correspondence with the War Service Board and information about the reconstruction.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the Smith College Relief Unit records came to the College Archives largely as gifts or bequests from the members of the Unit and their families. These donors include Dorothy Ainsworth, Mary Allsebrook, Edith Bannon, Marion Bennet, Eugene and Mary Clapp, Ellen Tucker Emerson, Raymond and Amelia Forbes Emerson, Alice Evans, Louisa Kimball Fast, Harriet Bliss Ford, Ruth Gaines, Ruth Whitney Higgins, Alice Emily Leavens, Georgia W. Read, Mary Stevenson, Frances Wadsworth Valentine and Dorothy Young.
Arrangement
The files are organized into eight categories: early history, financial records, directors, individuals, photographs, publications, news clippings and reconstruction. Financial records and news clippings are arranged chronologically and the directors' records are arranged in order of their terms of office. All other files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
World War, 1914-1918--Women.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.; Hawes, Harriet Boyd, 1871-1945.; Smith College. Relief Unit.
- History and Chronology, 1917-1929 (Box 133, Folder 1)
- American Fund for French Wounded, 1917 (Box 133, Folder 2)
- Financial Statements, Aug.1917-Feb.1921 (Box 133, Folder 3)
- Ledger (Box 133, Folder 4)
- Account with Morgan, Harjes & Co., 1919-1921 (Box 133, Folder 5)
- Financial Statements, Jun.1922-May 1930 (Box 133, Folder 6)
- Ledger, Jun.1918-May 1920 (Box 133)
- Ledger, May 1920-Jun.1929 (Box 133)
- Hawes, Harriet Boyd, Aug. - Sep. 1917 (Box 134, Folder 1)
- Tallant, Alice Weld: (Box 134)
  - Correspondence, general, Oct. 1917 - Jan. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Japan Smith Club, 1918-1919 (Box 134, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, War Service Board, 1917 (Box 134, Folder 4)
  - Photo and Autograph Album, Jan. 26. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 5)
  - Photos of, News Clippings about A.W.T., undated (Box 134, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1917-1918 (Box 134, Folder 7)
- Andrews, Hannah Dunlop:
  - Correspondence, Jan. - Aug. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Sep. - Nov. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, to family, 1917-1918 (Box 134, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, War Service Board, Jan. - Mar. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, War Service Board (Beauvais), Apr. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, War Service Board, May - Aug. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, War Service Board (Chateau Thierry), Sep. - Dec. 1918 (Box 134, Folder 15)
  - Departmental Reports, 1917-1918 (Box 134, Folder 16)
  - Health Service, 1918 (Box 134, Folder 17)
  - Red Cross, 1918 (Box 134, Folder 18)
  - Red Cross, reports to, 1918 (Box 134, Folder 19)
- Wolfs, Marie Leonie
  - Agriculture and Livestock, 1919 (Box 135, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture, reports, Jan. 1919 - Mar. 1920 (Box 135, Folder 2)
  - Appeals for Civilian Aid, 1919 (Box 135, Folder 3)
  - Automobiles, 1919 (Box 135, Folder 4)
  - Barracks, 1918-1919 (Box 135, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Data (Box 135, Folder 6)
  - Departmental Reports, Children, 1919 (Box 135, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan. - Mar. 1919 (Box 135, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Apr. - May 1919 (Box 135, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jun. - Sep. 1919 (Box 135, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Family, Aug. - Dec. 1917 (Box 135, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to Family, 1918 (Box 135, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Family, Jan. - Jul. 1919 (Box 135, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence to War Service Board (Beauvais), April 1918 (Box 135, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence to War Service Board, Jan. - May 1919 (Box 135, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence to War Service Board, Jun. - Aug. 1919 (Box 135, Folder 16)
  - Diaries, 1914; 1917; 1919 (Box 135, Folder 17)
  - Diary, typescript, 1918 (Box 135, Folder 18)
  - Dinner (in honor of M.L.W.), Jul. 15, 1919 (Box 135, Folder 19)
  - General (Box 136, Folder 1)
  - Guest books, 1917-1920 (Box 136, Folder 2)
  - Health Services, 1919-1920 (Box 136, Folder 3)
  - Libraries, 1919 (Box 136, Folder 4)
  - Maps of France, undated (Box 136, Folder 5)
  - Medals and Arm Band, 1920-1923 (Box 136, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 136, Folder 7)
  - Official Documents, 1914-1919 (Box 136, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 136, Folder 9)
  - Red Cross, Sep. 1918 - Jul. 1919 (Box 136, Folder 10)
  - Schools, May - Jun. 1919 (Box 136, Folder 11)
  - Social Services, Jan. 1919 - Mar. 1920 (Box 136, Folder 12)
  - Supplies, general, May - Nov. 1919 (Box 136, Folder 13)
  - Supplies, clothing, May - Jun. 1919 (Box 136, Folder 14)
  - Treasurer's Reports, May 1919-Feb. 1920 (Box 136, Folder 15)
  - War Indemnity, Apr. - Dec. 1919 (Box 136, Folder 16)
- Chapin, Anne McClallan
  - Agriculture, Sep. - Dec. 1919 (Box 137, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture, fruit trees, Jan. 1919- Jul. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Trustee, Aug. 1922- Jan. 1923 (Box 137, Folder 3)
  - Automobiles, Sep. 1919-Apr. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 4)
  - Barracks (Box 137, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Devastated Regions (Box 137, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul. - Oct. 1919 (Box 137, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Nov. - Dec. 1919 (Box 137, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan. - Feb. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Mar. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Apr. - May 1920 (Box 137, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, to family, Mar. - Aug. 1918 (Box 137, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, re: Ruth Gaines, Sep. 1919-Jun. 1922 (Box 137, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, thank-you letters, Sep. 1919-Apr. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, to War Service Board, Sep. 1917 - Feb. 1918 (Box 137, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, to War Service Board, Mar. - Apr. 1918 (Box 137, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, to War Service Board, Oct. - Dec. 1918 (Box 137, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, to War Service Board, Aug. - Dec. 1919 (Box 137, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, to War Service Board, Jan. - May 1920 (Box 137, Folder 19)
  - Dinner (in honor of A.M.C. and Hannah Andrews), Jan. 4, 1919 (Box 137, Folder 20)
  - Films, Jan. - Feb. 1920 (Box 137, Folder 21)
  - Health Service, Aug. - Dec. 1919 (Box 138, Folder 1)
  - Health Service, Jan. - Jun. 1920 (Box 138, Folder 2)
  - Health Service, Dentist, Aug. 1919-Jan. 1920 (Box 138, Folder 3)
  - Inhabitants of SCRU villages, Dec. 1919 (Box 138, Folder 4)
  - Medal of Honor, 1919-1920 (Box 138, Folder 5)
  - Official Documents, 1917-1922 (Box 138, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 138, Folder 7)
  - Questionnaire, 1921 (Box 138, Folder 8)
  - Schools, Sep. 1919-Mar. 1920 (Box 138, Folder 9)
  - Supplies, Jul. 1919-Apr. 1920 (Box 138, Folder 10)
- Individuals: A-D
  - Andrus, Ida Bourne, 1918-1922 (Box 139, Folder 1)
  - Ashley, Margaret, Sep. 15, 1917 (Box 139, Folder 2)
  - Bannon, Charlotte, Feb. 25, 1919 (Box 139, Folder 3)
  - Bennet, Marion, 1917-1920 (Box 139, Folder 4)
  - Biddlecome, Elizabeth, May 1918-Apr. 1921 (Box 139, Folder 5)
    - corr. to War Service Board (Box 139)
    - documents, 1918-1920 (Box 139, Folder 6)
    - photographs, undated (Box 139, Folder 7)
    - photograph album, [1914]-1920 (Box 139, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Dorothy Helen, 1918-1919 (Box 139, Folder 9)
  - Carr, Marjorie Leigh, 1917-1918 (Box 139, Folder 10)
  - Clapp, Marie Antoinette, Aug. - Nov. 1918 (Box 139, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence to family (Box 139)
    - Correspondence to family, Dec.1919 - Apr.1920 (Box 139, Folder 12)
    - photographs, 1919-1920 (Box 139, Folder 13)
  - Clark, Mary, Jun. 17, 1918 (Box 139, Folder 14)
  - Clement, Fannie Fletcher, Jan.1919-Jan.1920 (Box 139, Folder 15)
  - Ainsworth, Dorothy Sears
    - Correspondence to family, Jan. - Apr. 1919 (Box 140, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to family, May - Jul. 1919 (Box 140, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to family, Aug. - Oct. 1919 (Box 140, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to Family, Nov.1919-Jan.1920 (Box 140, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to family, May - Jul. 19236Aug. - Sep. 1923 (Box 140, Folder 5)
    - Official Documents, 1918-1920 (Box 140, Folder 7)
    - Photographs (Box 140, Folder 8)
  - Bliss, Elizabeth Howe (Box 141)
    - Correspondence to Blanche Lange, Aug. - Sep. 1917 (Box 141, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Blanche Lange, Oct.1917-Mar.1918 (Box 141, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to Blanche Lange, Apr. - Sep. 1918 (Box 141, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to Blanche Lange, Nov. 1918 (Box 141, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to mother, Jul.1917 - Apr. 1918 (Box 141, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence to Helen Rand Thayer, 1917-1918 (Box 141, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence re: War Service, 1966 (Box 141, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence miscellaneous, 1917-1964 (Box 141, Folder 8)
    - Diaries, Aug.1917-Sep.1918 (Box 141, Folder 9)
    - miscellaneous (Box 141, Folder 10)
    - Photographs, 1917-1918 (Box 141, Folder 11)
    - Official Documents, 1917-1918 (Box 141, Folder 12)
    - Red Cross, 1918-1923 (Box 141, Folder 13)
  - Dana, Elizabeth Mabel
    - Souvenirs (Box 142)
      - coins, buttons, bullets (Box 142)
      - chevrons and insignia (Box 142)
      - artifacts (Box 142)
    - Correspondence, general, Sep.1918-Jun.1926 (Box 142, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, to parents, Sep. 1917-Jul.1919 (Box 142, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, from Isabel Mitchell, undated (Box 142, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, from John J. Pershing, Apr. 28, 1919 (Box 142, Folder 4)
    - Financial Records, 1917-1920 (Box 142, Folder 5)
    - Red Cross, 1917-1919 (Box 142, Folder 6)
    - Official Documents, 1917-1919 (Box 142, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, 1917-1918 (Box 142, Folder 8)
    - Posters and Guidebooks, undated (Box 142, Folder 9)
    - Programs, 1917-1919 (Box 142, Folder 10)
    - Publications and Clippings, 1918 (Box 142, Folder 11)
    - Publications - Puranees Bulletin, Mar. - Apr. 1919 (Box 142, Folder 12)
    - Song Sheets, 1917-1919 (Box 142, Folder 13)
    - Tickets, undated (Box 142, Folder 14)
    - Y.M.C.A., 1917-1918 (Box 142, Folder 15)
- Individuals: E - F
  - Emerson, Ellen Tucker, Dec. 30, 1918 (Box 143, Folder 1)
    - birth certificate (Box 143)
    - corr. to family, Feb. - Apr. 1919 (Box 143, Folder 2)
    - corr. to family, May - Dec. 1919 (Box 143, Folder 3)
    - corr. - miscellaneous, Apr.1917 - May 1919 (Box 143, Folder 4)
    - photographs, undated (Box 143, Folder 5)
  - Emerson, Josephine Burt, Sep. 1920 (Box 143, Folder 6)
  - Evans, Alice, Aug. 1918-Sep. 1919 (Box 143, Folder 7)
    - "My years with the SCRU" (Box 143)
  - Farrand, Margaret Louise, Sep. 1923 (Box 143, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, to Marie de Grecourt (Box 143)
    - Correspondence, to Pierre de Schoemaker, Apr.1917-Mar. 1919 (Box 143, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, to general, 1917-1927 (Box 143, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, to Paul Junka, Jul.1919--Dec.1923 (Box 143, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, to Helene Legendre, undated (Box 143, Folder 12)
    - Fatherless Children of France, Inc., Jun.1916-Feb.1921 (Box 143, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, to Marcel Augagne, 1910-1924 (Box 143, Folder 14)
  - Fast, Louisa Kimball, Mar.1918-Nov.1919 (Box 143, Folder 15)
  - Ford, Harriet Bliss, 1917-1919 (Box 143, Folder 16)
- Individuals: G - T
  - Grandin, Mabel, Feb.1918-Jun.1919 (Box 144, Folder 1)
  - Grant, Rosamond, Feb.1919-Mar.1921 (Box 144, Folder 2)
  - Griffin, Edith, 1919-1920 (Box 144, Folder 3)
  - Hackett, Sarah Balch, Aug.1918-Aug.1919 (Box 144, Folder 4)
  - Higgins, Ruth Whitney, Dec.1918-Feb.1919 (Box 144, Folder 5)
  - Hooper, Catherine Baker, Aug. - Dec.1917 (Box 144, Folder 6)
    - corr. to family, Jan. - Mar.1918 (Box 144, Folder 7)
    - corr. to family, Jul. - Dec.1918 (Box 144, Folder 8)
    - corr. to family, 1919 (Box 144, Folder 9)
    - corr. to War Service Board, 1919 (Box 144, Folder 10)
    - photographs, undated (Box 144, Folder 11)
  - Joslin, Ruth, Jan.1918-Feb.1919 (Box 144, Folder 12)
  - Kelly, Maud M., 1917 (Box 144, Folder 13)
  - Kinney, Delan, 1920 (Box 144, Folder 14)
  - La Monte, Isabel, Dec.1918-May 1920 (Box 144, Folder 15)
  - Lavignet, Marguerite, undated (Box 144, Folder 16)
  - Lawrence, Evelyn Lucy, 1919 (Box 144, Folder 17)
  - Leavens, Alice Emily, Dec.1917-May 1919 (Box 144, Folder 18)
  - Lewis, Millicent Vaughn, 1917 (Box 144, Folder 19)
  - Mather, Lucy Olcott, Aug.1917-Jun.1918 (Box 144, Folder 20)
  - Ober, Alice May, Dec.1918-Feb.1919 (Box 144, Folder 21)
  - Rochester, Anna, Aug. 1918 (Box 144, Folder 22)
  - Ryan, Anna, Oct. 1918 (Box 144, Folder 23)
  - Studebaker, Adrianna Louise, Dec. 1918 (Box 144, Folder 24)
  - Talbot, Marjorie, Mar. - Apr.1918 (Box 144, Folder 25)
  - Thomas, Marion, Oct. 9, 1918 (Box 144, Folder 26)
  - True, Edna Miriam, Aug. 1918-Feb 1919 (Box 144, Folder 27)
  - Gaines, Ruth Louise
    - Appointments and Recommendations, 1904-1919 (Box 145, Folder 1)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1917-1919 (Box 145, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, general, Sep.1917-May 1920 (Box 145, Folder 3)
      - with family, Aug.1917 - Aug.1918 (Box 145, Folder 4)
      - with family, Jul. - Dec. 1917 (Box 145, Folder 5)
      - with Georgia Read, Sep. - Dec. 1917 (Box 145, Folder 6)
      - with War Service Board, Nov.1917-Apr.1919 (Box 145, Folder 7)
      - from French villagers, Oct.1917-Nov.1920 (Box 145, Folder 8)
    - Diaries, 1918-1919 (Box 145, Folder 9)
    - Maps of France, 1919 (Box 145, Folder 10)
    - miscellaneous, 1919 (Box 145, Folder 11)
    - Notes, 1917-1919 (Box 145, Folder 12)
    - Official Documents, 1917-1919 (Box 145, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 145, Folder 14)
    - Reports, departmental reports, Feb. - Oct. 1918 (Box 145, Folder 15)
    - Reports, Relief of Devastated Regions, 1914-1919 (Box 145, Folder 16)
    - Reports, Village Mayors, 1919 (Box 145, Folder 17)
    - Reports, War Service Board, Aug.1917-Oct.1918 (Box 145, Folder 18)
    - Publications
      - Helping France, Civil Affairs Report, Sep. - Dec. 1917 (Box 146, Folder 1)
        - correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 146, Folder 2)
        - notes, 1917 (Box 146, Folder 3)
        - notes, 1918-1919 (Box 146, Folder 4)
        - notes, 1919 (Box 146, Folder 5)
        - Red Cross, 1918-1919 (Box 146, Folder 6)
      - Helping France and Ladies of Grecourt, 1919; 1920 (Box 146, Folder 7)
      - Ladies of Grecourt, Aug.1918-Jun.1919 (Box 146, Folder 8)
        - corr. with War Service Board (Box 146)
        - corr. with War Service Board, Sep.1919-May 1920 (Box 146, Folder 9)
        - contracts, 1919 (Box 146, Folder 10)
        - illustrations, Sep.1919-Oct.921 (Box 146, Folder 11)
        - preface, Mar. - Jun. 1920 (Box 146, Folder 12)
        - publication and sale, May 1920-Jul.1921 (Box 146, Folder 13)
      - Ladies of Grecourt, Publication and Sale, Sep.1921-Nov.1922 (Box 146, Folder 14)
        - settlement, 1923 (Box 146, Folder 15)
      - Village in Picardy (Box 146)
        - Correspondence, Feb.1918-Aug.1919 (Box 147, Folder 1)
        - Illustrations, undated (Box 147, Folder 2)
        - Newspaper articles - typescripts, 1917-1918 (Box 147, Folder 3)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1917-1919 (Box 147, Folder 4)
        - Notes, 1914-1919 (Box 147, Folder 5)
        - Proposal, Sep.25; 1918 (Box 147, Folder 6)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 147, Folder 7)
        - Village in Picardy (Box 147)
  - Greenborough, Clara
    - Beauvais - American Club, Mar.1918-Dec.1919 (Box 148, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, to family, Jan. - Mar.1918 (Box 148, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, to family, Apr. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, to family, May - Jul. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, to family, Aug. - Dec. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, to family, Jan. - Aug. 1919 (Box 148, Folder 6)
    - corr. with National War Work Council, Mar. - Jul. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 7)
    - corr. with War Service Board, Apr. - Jun. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, Mar.1918-Jun.1922 (Box 148, Folder 9)
    - Flags, Nov. 1918 (Box 148, Folder 10)
    - Medals and Stripes (Box 148, Folder 11)
    - Official Documents, 1918-1919 (Box 148, Folder 12)
    - Overseas Service, Jun. 1922 (Box 148, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1914-1918 (Box 148, Folder 14)
  - Read, Georgia W.
    - Correspondence with mother, Sep.1918-Mar.1919 (Box 149, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to War Service Board, Sep. - Oct. 1918 (Box 149, Folder 2)
    - Diaries, Oct.1918-Mar.1919 (Box 149, Folder 3)
    - miscellaneous, Mar. 1918 (Box 149, Folder 4)
    - Official Documents, 1918-1924 (Box 149, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 149, Folder 6)
    - Publication: Kantine Braunschweig, undated (Box 149, Folder 7)
    - Red Cross, Aug.1918-Oct.1920 (Box 149, Folder 8)
    - Treasurer's Reports, Feb. - Apr. 1919 (Box 149, Folder 9)
  - Stevenson, Mary Goodman
    - Citations, 1919 (Box 150, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with family, Jun.1918-Dec.1919 (Box 150, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to War Service Board, Aug.1918-Aug.1919 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    - Official Documents, 1918-1919 (Box 150, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 150, Folder 5)
    - Photograph Album, Jun.1918-Jul.1919 (Box 150)
- Individuals: V - Z
  - Valentine, Frances Wadsworth, 1918-1920 (Box 151)
    - citations (Box 151, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to family, Jul.1917-Apr.1918 (Box 151, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to family, Jul.1918-Apr.1919 (Box 151, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to War Service Board, Dec.1917-May 1922 (Box 151, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, general, May 1918- Dec.1920 (Box 151, Folder 5)
    - Diary, Nov.1917-Jan.1918 (Box 151, Folder 6)
    - Identification Bracelet (Box 151, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, 1917-1954 (Box 151, Folder 8)
    - Photograph Albums, undated (Box 151, Folder 9)
    - Travel Permits, 1917-1919 (Box 151, Folder 10)
    - Visas, 1917-1920 (Box 151, Folder 11)
  - Wiggin, Charlotte Monroe (Box 151, Folder 12)
    General
    [See Serbian Relief Unit]
  - Williams, Esther Sprague (Box 151, Folder 13)
  - Wolfs, Marie Leonie (Box 151, Folder 14)
    [See Directors files]
  - Wood, Margaret, 1917-1918 (Box 151, Folder 15)
  - Young, Dorothy A., Jun. 1918-Jan.1919 (Box 151, Folder 16)
    - correspondence to family (Box 151)
    - correspondence to War Service Board, Aug. 1918 (Box 151, Folder 17)